Guide to the Anson Phelps Stokes Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Anson Phelps Stokes family papers
1761-1960
1892-1958
MS 299
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
145.25
(321 boxes, 4 folios)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, subject files, memorabilia, photographs, financial records, and other papers detailing the professional career and personal life of Anson Phelps Stokes and family members, including Olivia, Caroline and Helen Stokes. Papers relating to Anson Phelps Stokes document his work with prominent educators, reformers, religious leaders, businessmen, and politicians. Stokes's work on behalf of black education, social issues, and the Phelps-Stokes Fund are detailed. His religious activities, Yale University work, and family interests are also represented, as are Stokes's work on behalf of the Portsmouth Treaty of 1905 and the Yale-China Association. Papers relating to Helen Phelps Stokes include material relating to the Socialist Party and the National Civil Liberties Bureau.
Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anson Phelps Stokes and other Stokes family members, 1942-1975. Gift of the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1994.
Biographical / Historical
Anson Phelps Stokes was born April 13, 1874, at New Brighton, Staten Island, New York. He shared a name with and was the son of Anson Phelps Stokes, a wealthy New York merchant and banker, and Helen Louisa Phelps Stokes.
After graduating from St. Paul's School in 1892, Stokes entered Yale University. A member of the class of 1896, he was chairman of the Yale Daily News as an undergraduate. Stokes received a B.A. degree from Yale in 1896 and a Bachelor of Divinity degree from the Episcopal Theological School in 1900.
In 1899, at the age of twenty-five, Stokes became Secretary of Yale University under President Arthur T. Hadley. Stokes held this position for twenty-two years, during which time he was largely responsible for the establishment of the Alumni Advisory Board and was instrumental in securing substantial gifts and endowments for the University. In 1900, Anson Phelps Stokes was ordained to the deaconate in the Protestant Episcopal Church. In addition to his duties at Yale, he served at St. Paul's Episcopal Church in New Haven from 1900 to 1918. During this period he was active on numerous New Haven and Yale committees. Yale-in-China, an organization to which he was to give many years of service as a member of the executive committee, was organized in 1902 at a meeting in his home. Stokes, along with Clifford Beers, was one of the founders of the National Committee on Mental Hygiene. A founder of the Lowell House Association and the Institute of Government Research, Stokes also served on the Committee on Japanese Peace Plans. (See Series III, "Yale, the Portsmouth Treaty, and Japan.")
In 1911 the Phelps-Stoke Fund, established by the will of Caroline Phelps Stokes, was incorporated. According to the wishes of Stokes's aunt, the fund would be used for "the erection and improvement of tenement house dwellings in the city of New York for the poor families of that city…and for the education of Negroes, both in Africa and the United States, North American Indians and needy and deserving white students, through industrial school the founding of scholarships, and the erection of endowment of school buildings and chapels" (Act of Incorporation of the Phelps-Stokes Fund Trustees, 1911). Anson Phelps Stokes was an active and devoted trustee of the Fund from its inception; in 1924, he became president of the board and served in this capacity until 1946.
Stokes resigned as Secretary of Yale University in 1921 at the close of the Hadley administration. He was considered for the presidency of Yale, which went instead to James Rowland Angell. In the interim period between his resignation from Yale and his acceptance of the position at Washington Cathedral, Stokes maintained his involvement in a variety of educational boards and commissions. In addition to his work on the board of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, Stokes had been a trustee of the General Education Board since May of 1912. At the request of the War Work Council of the Y.M.C.A., Stokes had made a study of the educational needs and opportunities of the American Expeditionary Forces. After publishing his findings in 1918 as Educational Plans for the American Army Abroad, he organized the Army Educational Commission. One of the organizers of the American University Union in Europe, he served as chairman of its board of trustees from 1917 to 1919. Because of his educational work in France, Stokes received the award of Chevalier of the Legion of Honor from the French government.
Stokes's involvement in international educational projects is further evidenced by his service on the administrative board of the Institute of International Education and the Central China College Board. As for educational institutions in the United States, Stokes was deeply concerned with the welfare of St. Paul's School, where he was a member of the board of trustees, and with Hampton and Tuskegee Institutes, in whose behalf he acted as the Chairman of the Special Gifts Committee of the Hampton-Tuskegee Endowment campaign.
Because of his clerical and educational affiliations, Anson Phelps Stokes was a logical choice to assist Charles Foster Kent of Yale University in organizing the National Council on Religion in Higher Education.
In 1924 Anson Phelps Stokes accepted the post of Canon of the Cathedral of St. Peter and St. Paul in Washington, D.C., a position which he held until his retirement in 1939. In March, 1925, he was ordained a priest of the Protestant Episcopal Church. Stokes's skills as a fund-raiser were, as they had been at Yale, put to good use. His advice, tact, and organizational ability were responsible for securing special gifts and endowments for the National Cathedral building campaign.
During his years in Washington, Canon Stokes served on a host of committees, organizing some and chairing many. The unifying threads of this extensive committee work were three basic concerns in his life: education, social welfare, and religion.
A number of committees on which he served were directly related to his position as Canon, such as the various committees of the Chapter of Washington Cathedral, St. Monica's League, and the Diocesan Committee on Social Welfare. In addition, Stokes was the organizer and chairman of the Committee on Religious Life in the Nation's Capital.
While in Washington, Stokes was active in several charitable and welfare organizations: chairman of the Committee for the Relief of Russian Refugees in Constantinople, chairman of the board of trustees of St. Anna's Home for Aged Colored Women, president of the Family Service Association, and a member of the board of the Community Chest.
Stokes was committed to eliminating the exclusion of black people from the public and private social agencies of the nation's capital. To this end he organized the Interracial Committee of the Washington Federation of Churches, which co-ordinated the efforts of black and white churchmen in such concerns as a survey of Negro housing conditions, a study of discrimination in public theaters in Washington, and an exhibit of Negro art at the Smithsonian Institute. Stokes was also the chairman and organizer of the committee on integrating Negro churches into the Washington Federation of Churches.
One of the interests of the Phelps-Stokes Fund was low-cost housing for poor families in New York City. Anson Phelps Stokes expanded this concern into his Washington committee work, serving as president of the Washington Housing Association and as chairman of President Roosevelt's committee to plan the Alley Dwelling Authority. His efforts were directed towards the inclusion of housing for Negroes in federally funded projects. Stokes was concerned with another of the city's problems; he acted as chairman of the Citizen's Committee on Unemployment.
In the areas of education and research, Anson Phelps Stokes was a trustee of the Brookings Institution and the Booker Washington Institute of Liberia. He was chairman of the Committee on Leisure-Time Facilities for Government Employees. Stokes and the Phelps-Stokes Fund were involved in a project to compile an Encyclopedia of the Negro. W.E.B. DuBois and Guy B. Johnson were the editors; Stokes was chairman of a board of directors that included R.R. Moton, J.H. Dillard, and Benjamin Brawley. Only a preparatory volume appeared.
Due to the demands made upon his time by these extensive commitments, Stokes was forced to withdraw his participation from a number of boards. He resigned from the China Medical Board in April, 1930. In April of 1932, he resigned from the remaining Rockefeller boards of which he was a trustee: the International Education Board, the General Education Board, and the Rockefeller Foundation.
In 1939, Anson Phelps Stokes resigned from his position at Washington Cathedral to retire to Lenox, Massachusetts. There he devoted himself to two major research projects, which he had been pursuing in his spare time for many years: a history of universities and the history of church and state relations in the United States.
During the war years, Stokes was the organizer and chairman of the Committee on Negro Americans in the Defense Industry and the Committee on Africa, the War and Peace Aims. The latter committee published The Atlantic and Africa from an American Viewpoint in 1942.
In his years of retirement at Lenox, Stokes was involved in a number of conservationist efforts, among them the Stockbridge Bowl Association and the Pleasant Valley Bird and Wildflower Sanctuary in Berkshire County.
Anson Phelps Stokes's three-volume history, Church and State in the United States, was finally published by Harper and Brothers in 1950. In 1951 Stokes received the Churchman of the Year Award, followed by the Yale Medal in 1952. His book on the history of universities was never completed.
In the course of his long life, Stokes was a world traveler, beginning with a visit to the Holy Land as a young man in 1891. He traveled around the world after graduating from Yale in 1896 and toured the Far East in 1920. Nine years later, Stokes visited South America; during 1932 and 1933 he was Visiting Carnegie Lecturer to the Universities of the Union of South Africa. One result of the African tour was the Report of Rev. Anson Phelps Stokes on Education, Native Welfare, and Race Relations in East and South Africa, published by the Carnegie Corporation in 1934.
Anson Phelps Stokes was married to Carol Green Mitchell in December 1903. They had two sons, Anson Phelps Stokes and Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes, and one daughter, Olivia E. Phelps Stokes, who became Mrs. John D. Hatch. Anson Phelps Stokes died August 13, 1958, at the age of eighty-four.
For a list of published writings by Anson Phelps Stokes, see the bibliography compiled by Stokes (refer to his statement in the Description of the Papers). A list of writings on the Negro and race relations and a complete listing of committee and boards of which Stokes was a member follows this biographical sketch. Additional biographical information may be found in Series IV (box 207, folder 150), which contains "Anson Phelps Stokes's Services to the Phelps-Stokes Fund (1946)" and the Yale University News Bureau release on the event of Stokes's death.
* * * * *
List of Committees and Boards, A.P.S., 1892-1942 (Made at request of C.M.P.S.)
I. Yale Undergraduate and Theological School Days
Yale Daily News Chairman
Yale Cooperative Corporation
Yale Debating Team Against Harvard
Yale Junior Promenade Committee Floor Manager
Yale Civil Service Reform Association Organizer and President
Board of Directors, Y.M.C.A., and Board of Deacons
Bible Study Committee of Y.M.C.A. Chairman
Yale Alumni Fund Class Agent
Mount Hermon School Board
Wellesley College Trustees
Committee on Commons (E.T.S.) Chairman
Missionary Society (E.T.S.) President
II. Early Years in New Haven as Secretary of Yale
Yale Corporation Secretary
University Council Secretary
Alumni Advisory Board Secretary
Prudential Committee of Yale Corporation Secretary
Alumni University Day Proposer, Organizer, and always Chairman or Secretary of Committee in charge
Y.M.C.A. Debt Campaign Vice Chairman
Yale-in-China (organized in house) Chairman Executive Committee; Chairman
Lowell House Association (organized at house)
Yale Bicentennial Committee Secretary
Phelps-Stokes Fund Secretary, Chairman
Phelps-Stokes Fund, Education Committee Chairman
Yale Athletic Committee
New Haven Hospital Board
Board of Trustees of New Haven Dispensary
Committee on Mental Hygiene (first Society organized in our house, and presided at the first meeting of National Committee)
Trustees of the Hillhouse Property
Russell Trust Association, Committee on New Building
New Haven Organized Charities
Committee on Civil War Memorial Secretary
Committee on Japanese Peace Plans Professors Williams, Wolsey, and self
International Committee of Y.M.C.A.
Committee on the Yale Bowl
Institute of Government Research one of group of three founders, others being Charles Norton and Jerome Greene
Committee on the War and the Religious Outlook
III. Later Years in New Haven
Committee on Yale Pageant Secretary
Yale University Press, Committee on Publications Secretary
Committee on Yale University Endowment Organizer and Agent
Committee on University Memorials Secretary
Committee on Plan for University Development (Reorganization) Secretary
Conference Committee on Yale and New Haven
Committee on Protection of Yale Name
University Committee on Educational Policy Secretary
Committee on Inauguration of President Angell Chairman
IV. Two Years Study After Leaving New Haven
Ascension Farm School
National Council on Religion in Higher Education assisted Professor Kent in organizing, and offered Chairmanship
Hampton-Tuskegee Endowment Campaign Chairman Special Gifts Committee
International Education Board
General Education Board
Rockefeller Foundation
China Medical Board (Brief Period)
American University Union in Europe Organizer and Chairman
Institute of International Education Chairman
American Academy in Rome
Central China College Board
Educational Commission of Y.M.C.A. A.E.F. Organizer
Tuskegee Institute Declined Chairmanship
Trustees of St. Paul's School
Board of Religious Education of the Episcopal Church
Phelps Stokes Estates and Corporation
V. Washington Days
Chapter of Washington Cathedral
Committee on St. Albans School Chairman
Library Committee Chairman
Washington Cathedral Endowment Committee Vice Chairman
Committee on Girl's School Secretary
Committee on the Massing of the Colors Service Chairman
College of Preachers Committee Secretary
Miscellaneous
St. Anna's Home Chairman
Washington Interracial Committee Organizer and Chairman
Washington Housing Association Chairman
Board Appointed by the President to Determine Form of Alley Dwelling Authority Chairman
Diocesan Committee on Social Welfare Chairman
Diocesan Committee on the Maryland Vestry Act
Committee on Diocesan-Wide Mission Chairman
Committee on Leisure Time Facilities for Government Employees Chairman
Committee for the Relief of Russian Refugees in Constantinople Chairman
Committee to Save St. Stephen's Church Chairman
Citizens Committee on Unemployment Chairman
Encyclopaedia of the Negro Organizer and Chairman
Federation of Churches Board Declined Chairmanship
Committee on Negro Representation on the Washington Federation of Churches
Committee on Christian Unity and Associate Delegate Oxford Conference
St. Monica's League Chairman
Board of Sponsors of Episcopal Eye Ear and Throat Hospital
Committee on Northwest Settlement one of organizers
Community Chest Board
Committee on Relations of the Hospital to the Community Chest Chairman
Advisory Board of District of Columbia Board of Health
Committee on Religious Life in the Nation's Capital Organizer and Chairman
Brookings Institution Trustees, and Executive Committee
Booker Washington Institute in Kakata, Liberia
Advisory Committee on Education in Liberia Vice Chairman
Committee on the Marian Anderson Episode Advisor and Representative before D.A.R.
Committee on the Cathedral and the Washington Bicentennial Chairman
VI. Later Years Lenox and New York
Lenox Library Board
Pleasant Valley Bird and Wild Flower Sanctuary Chairman
Vestry of Trinity Church
Committee on Yale University History
Episcopal Committee on European Refugees
Committee on the Negro American in Defense Industries Chairman
Committee on Africa, the War, and Peace Aims Chairman
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in two parts and three additions.
Part I is arranged in six series and oversize materials: I. Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes, 1892-1958. II. Journals, Speeches, Writings, and Research Materials, 1890-1958. III. Subjects Files, 1767-1958. IV. Memorabilia and Photos,1761-1958. V. Financial and Property Records, 1804-1958. VI. Stokes Family Papers, 1834-1960.
Part II is arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, 1893-1957. II. Journals, Speeches, Writings and Research Materials, 1896-1954. III. Subject files, 1911-1954. IV. Memorabilia and Photographs, 1896-1954. V. Financial and Property Records, 1923-1955. VI. Stokes Family Papers, 1900-1921.
Scope and Contents
The Anson Phelps Stokes Papers consist of correspondence, writings, subjects files, memorabilia, photographs, financial records, and family papers. The material has been divided into six series, the largest being the correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes, which comprises more than half of the papers in the collection.
Part I, Series I, Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes, includes both the general and family correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes spanning almost eighty years from 1879 to 1958. The correspondence reflects the diverse interests of the Stokes family and Anson Phelps Stokes's participation on numerous boards and committees. (See the biographical sketch above.) As a result of these activities, Stokes became acquainted with educators, reformers, religious leaders, prominent businessmen, financiers, politicians, and diplomats. Much of the resultant correspondence concerns administrative matters; a much smaller portion is concerned with leading issues of the day.
There is significant correspondence with American educational leaders, both black and white. Because of his years at Yale and his influential work on a number of major educational boards, Stokes's correspondence reflects the early organizational efforts, the formulation of policy, and the implementation of significant projects in education.
Anson Phelps Stokes corresponded at length with fellow officials and trustees of the American University Union (Horatio S. Krans and J.W. Cunliffe), the Institute of International Education (Stephen P. Duggan and George H. Nettleton), the Rockefeller Foundation (George E. Vincent and Max Mason), and the General and International Education Boards (Trevor Arnett, Wallace Buttrick, W.W. Brierley, James H. Dillard, Abraham Flexner, Raymond B. Fosdick, and Wickliffe Rose). The American Council on Education is represented in the correspondence with Samuel P. Capen and Charles R. Mann, among others.
As President of the Phelps-Stokes Fund and a trustee of several Rockefeller Foundation boards, Anson Phelps Stokes corresponded with some leading figures in the larger foundations: Frederick P. Keppel, President of the Carnegie Corporation, Julius Rosenwald of the Rosenwald Fund, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
As one would expect, there is considerable correspondence related to Yale. (Stokes's official correspondence as Secretary of Yale University is in the Yale University Archives and does not form a part of this collection.) Even after leaving Yale, however, Anson Phelps Stokes maintained a strong interest in the University's well-being and frequently corresponded with administrators, alumni, and the faculty of Yale. Part I, Series I contains Stokes's correspondence with three Yale presidents: Arthur Twining Hadley, with whom Stokes worked for twenty-two years, James Rowland Angell, and Charles Seymour. Many Yale professors and officials are represented in the correspondence, among them Clive Day, Wilbur L. Cross, George Dudley Seymour, Andrew Keogh and George Parmly Day. Two other prominent individuals, known to Stokes through Yale affiliations, are William Howard Taft and Henry L. Stimson. One of the founders of Yale-in-China, Anson Phelps Stokes corresponded throughout the turbulent years of its history with its directors and staff, including Dr. Edward H. Hume, Dr. F.D. Yen, F. Wells Williams, Palmer Bevis and others.
For forty-five years, Stokes was an integral part of the leadership of the Phelps-Stokes Fund. Created by the will of Caroline Phelps Stokes, an aunt of Anson Phelps Stokes, and incorporated in 1911, the Fund was dedicated specifically to the improvement of the housing of the poor in New York City and to the education of Negroes, North American Indians, and deserving white students. Educational aid was to be primarily in the form of scholarships and endowments for school buildings and improvements. Stokes carried on a lengthy and detailed correspondence with the Fund's director, Dr. Thomas Jesse Jones, and with its secretary and treasurer, L. A. Roy and F. Louis Slade, about personalities, projects, and policies.
As a result of the Phelps-Stokes Fund's programs in support of Negro education in the United States and Africa, Stokes became acquainted with many prominent black educators. Among those with whom he corresponded are: Robert R. Moton, Monroe N. Work, and Frederick Douglass Patterson of Tuskegee Institute; William Anthony Aery, James E. Gregg, and Arthur Howe of Hampton Institute; Mordecai W. Johnson and Benjamin Brawley of Howard University; and Thomas E. Jones of Fisk University. Other black leaders who corresponded with Stokes are Walter White and James Weldon Johnson of the N.A.A.C.P., Carter Woodson of the Journal of Negro History, Mary McLeod Bethune, and W.E.B. DuBois.
Throughout his life, Anson Phelps Stokes received many pleas for financial support from both institutions and individuals. Although unable to comply with requests for financial aid in many instances, he frequently gave his time and advice in constructive ways. Requests for Stokes's opinions and suggestions are a salient feature of the correspondence.
Over the years, Stokes lent his support to refugee relief work in Europe, the Middle East, and Asia. He had a special interest in the relief program for Russian refugees in Constantinople, because it was directed for many years by his wife's sister, Anna V.S. Mitchell. Her correspondence with Stokes and that of many others involved in relief work appear in the general correspondence.
A prominent Episcopal priest, Stokes corresponded with Roman Catholic, Protestant and Jewish clergymen, with members of the Federal Council of Churches, the Y.M.C.A., and the International Missionary Council, as well as with editors of religious publications. Among his correspondents in religious education were: Henry Sloane Coffin, William Adams Brown, and Reinhold Niebuhr of Union Theological Seminary.
As Canon of the Cathedral of St. Peter and St. Paul in Washington, D.C., one of Stokes's major duties was to assist in the National Cathedral fund-raising campaign. A sizable portion of his correspondence from 1924 to 1939 deals with the organization of the fund-raising campaign on a nation-wide scale and with the solicitation of endowments and special gifts for the Cathedral.